Massimo Salvadori Papers, 1908-1992 (bulk 1952-1972)
Smith College Archives
Massimo Salvadori Papers
1908-1992
1952-1972
Salvadori, Massimo.
RG 42 UUID:abf8117c-0e21-4b52-b472-fdc2675da890
7 boxes (2.9 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
The Massimo Salvadori Papers document his commitment to freedom and anti-fascism. The bulk of the materials consist of copies of the shorter publications as well as annotated manuscripts for a number of his other works. Other materials include biographical material, Smith College faculty photographs, publications, typewritten manuscripts and galley proofs, course materials for Smith College history classes, and correspondence related to the School for Freedom seminars.
Massimo "Max" W. Salvadori was born in London, England June 16, 1908, the son of positivist philosopher and writer Guglielmo dei Conti Salvadori-Paleotti and Giacinta Galleti di Cadilhac. He grew up in Italy, attending school in Florence until 1924 when clashes with Fascist fellow students caused him to leave. He lived in exile in Switzerland for five years, earning a Licence es Sciences Sociales at the University of Geneva in 1929.
Salvadori's early experiences shaped his hatred of all dictatorships. In 1929, he joined an underground anti-fascist group, Justice and Liberty. He then returned to Italy, ostensibly to attend the University of Rome, but also to organize in secrecy similar organizations against Mussolini. In 1930, he received a Doctorate of Political Sciences from the University of Rome. His political activities, however, caught the attention of the authorities and he was arrested and jailed from 1931-1932. Shortly afterward, he crossed into Switzerland and lived abroad for the next decade.
In 1943, Salvadori was living in England with his British wife Joyce Pawle. He joined the British Army as a lieutenant colonel and participated in the landings at Salerno and Anzio. He parachuted into the Italian countryside in 1945 to help organize a popular uprising. For his service, he was awarded the Military Cross and Distinguished Service Order.
Salvadori came to Smith College in 1945 after teaching at St. Lawrence University, New York from 1931-1941, and Bennington College. In 1948-49, Salvadori took a leave of absence from Smith in order to serve as the director of the Division of Political Science of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) in France. He also served as a political analyst for the Information Service of the Secretariat of NATO in 1952-53.
Salvadori wrote and lectured extensively. In 1956, his lecture, "American Capitalism," presented at the School for International Studies of the State Department's Foreign Service, was recognized by President Dwight D. Eisenhower. The White House issued and distributed a condensed form of Salvadori's remarks. He wrote texts on political history, as well as travel books, personal memoirs, pamphlets, reviews and articles in Italian, English, French, and Spanish. His 1962 work, The Rise of Modern Communism, has been translated into 16 languages.
Max Salvadori had a long association with the Liberal International, a London-based association of Liberal and Radical groups and parties. He joined the group in 1948. At his suggestion, the Liberal International started the School for Freedom program, student summer institutes for young liberals. These programs were held in different countries each year. Salvadori remained involved with the group throughout his life, directing eight sessions of the School for Freedom from 1955-1967.
At Smith, Salvadori was professor of modern European history until his retirement in 1973. He held the Dwight Morrow Professorship in History from 1964-1973. He also led the Junior Year for International Studies program in Geneva, Switzerland from 1973-1975.
Salvadori died in 1992, at age 84, survived by his wife Joyce Pawle, a son and daughter. In 1993, the college dedicated the Personal Computer Laboratory and Training Center in Seelye Hall in his memory.
The Massimo "Max" W. Salvadori Papers contain biographical materials, Smith College faculty photographs, publications, typewritten manuscripts and galley proofs, course materials for Smith College history classes, and correspondence related to the School for Freedom seminars. The bulk of the materials consists of copies of the shorter publications as well as annotated manuscripts for a number of his other works. The papers for the School for Freedom, a student institute organized in 1952 by the World International (World Liberal Union) include Salvadori's essay, "The School for Freedom: Origins, Purpose and Method," as well as correspondence relating to the session held June 16-25,1967 at Queen's University, Ontario, Canada.
This collection is organized into six series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. Photographs
III. Publications
IV. Writings
V. Course Materials
VI. The School for Freedom
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
History of the Collection
The Massimo Salvadori papers were acquired over time from various sources.
Search Terms
Salvadori, Massimo.; Smith College--Faculty.; School for Freedom.; History--Study and teaching (Higher)--Massachusetts--Northampton.
- Series I: Biographical Materials 1956-1993
  Biographical items consist of official Smith College News Office and History Department releases, a curriculum vitae, letters to the editors of the Daily Hampshire Gazette and the Smith College Quarterly, and a 1986 feature article, "Max Salvadori - In the Name of Liberty" from Hampshire Life magazine. Of particular interest are several news articles from the New York Herald Tribune relating to Salvadori's 1956 lecture,"American Capitalism," at the School for International Studies of the U.S. State Department.
  - Biographical Materials 1956-1993 (Box 1)
- Series II: Photographsca 1960, undated
  Photographs of Max Salvadori are from the S mith Faculty Quarterly. Two other photographs show Salvadori, professor of Italian Michele Cantarella (1929-1963), and an unidentified man. A fourth shows Salvadori seated at a panel with Smith College faculty members Klemens von Kemperer, professor of history; William Dennis Johnston, professor of theatre; Kenneth Connelly, professor of English; and Guenter Lewy, professor of government. All the photographs are undated.
  - Photographs ca 1960, undated (Box 1)
- Series III: Publications 1937-1973
  Materials include essays, symposium and conference papers and copies of the shorter works. Publications are in both original languages and in translations, including French, Spanish, Italian and Taiwanese. Of special interest is a copy of Salvadori's 1939 doctoral thesis from the University of Rome and his 1949 war memoir, "Resistenza ed Azione, Ricordidi un Liberale."
  - A-R 1937-1973 (Box 1)
    - "Answering a Questionnaire," for the Bennington College Bulletin 1960 (Box 1)
    - Aspects of International Communism (Taipei), text in Taiwanese 1953 (Box 1)
    - Autunno Americano (Rome) text in Italian, 197 (Box 1)
    - "A Comment on the Radicalism of the Left Addressed to the 'New Left'" 1967 (Box 1)
    - "Comments on the Free Use of Reason: Key to Progress" 1966 (Box 1)
    - "Components of the Ideology of Italian Fascism" 1964 (Box 1)
    - "Considerations on Socialism in Post War Italy" 1966 (Box 1)
    - "Europe's Age of Liberalism" 1952 (Box 1)
    - "Excerpts from a lecture on American Capitalism" 1956 (Box 1)
    - Il Movimento Comunista nel Ventisimo Secolo (Firenza), text in Italian 1954 (Box 1)
    - "Il Problema piu grave pro l'Italia," text in Italian 1965 (Box 1)
    - "Integralism-Despotism-Reactionism: Reply to the Enemy of Democracy" 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Las Ciencas Sociales del Siglo XX en Italia," (Mexico), text in Spanish undated (Box 1)
    - "L'Administration Coloniale et l'Evolution Sociale des Indigenenes au Kenya et dans l' Ouganda," text in French 1937 (Box 1)
    - L'Angleterre en mars 1939 et mars 1940 (Geneva), text in French 1940 (Box 1)
    - L' attuale Moviment Pacificta negli Stati Uniti ( Milano), text in Italian 1972 (Box 1)
    - "The New Capitalism" for Long Lines Magazine 1956 (Box 1)
    - The North Atlantic Treaty Organization: A Western View (New Delhi) 1953 (Box 1)
    - Problemi di Liberta, (Bari), text in Italian 1949 (Box 1)
    - Resistenza ed Azione, Ricordidi un Liberale, (Bari), text in Italian 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Revisionism" 1977 (Box 1)
  - S-Z 1937-1973
    - 'A Stone of Stumbling '(1 Peter,ii :8): the Debate on Democracy between the Second and Third International 1919-1922 1969 (Box 2)
    - "A Symposium on Tom Paine" 1973 (Box 2)
- Series IV: Writings: Manuscripts 1961-1965
  Materials consist of typewritten, annotated manuscripts and galley proofs for various editions and drafts of Salvadori's major works, including the original manuscrips for Cavour and the Unification of Italy, Modern Socialism, and The Rise of Modern Communism.
  - The American Economic System undated (Box 2)
  - Cavour and the Unification of Italy (2) undated (Box 2)
  - European Liberalism (3) undated (Box 2)
  - Europe's Needs and Resources (chap 1) undated (Box 2)
  - Italy 1965 (Box 2)
  - Liberal Heresy: Now and Later (draft) 1988 (Box 2)
  - The Liberal Heresy: Origins and Historical Development (galley proof) undated (Box 3)
  - Modern Socialism (6) undated (Box 3)
  - People's Capitalism: Anthology (9) undated (Box 4)
  - People's Capitalism (Box 5)
  - Pictorial History of the Italian People (4) undated (Box 5)
  - Rise of Modern Communism (2nd ed., draft) undated (Box 5)
  - Rise of Modern Communism (2nd ed.) undated (Box 5)
  - Rise of Modern Communism (2nd ed.) undated (Box 6)
  - Rise of Modern Communism (3rd ed) (2) undated (Box 6)
  - Rise Of Modern Communism (galley proof) (3) undated (Box 6)
  - Western Roots in Europe undated (Box 6)
- Series V: Course Materials 1966-1972
  This series consists of paper-bound lectures, lecture summaries and background notes for students in history classes taught by Professor Salvadori at Smith College. The majority of the course guides pertain to the Modern European history classes.
  - "Africa South of the Sahara" Historical background for Smith College History 231a, 232b, 334b 1971 (Box 7)
  - "Elements of the Impact Made Beyond its Borders after World War II by the United States (History 334b) 1972 (Box 7)
  - "European Liberalism: An Introduction" (History 231a,231b) undated (Box 7)
  - "The March of Liberalism" (draft) (History 252)a 1966-67 (Box 7)
  - "Methodology in History" (History 231a, 231b) 1972 (Box 7)
  - "Modern European History" undated (Box 7)
  - "Socialism: An Introduction" undated (Box 7)
- Series VI: The School for Freedom 1965-1969
  Papers include a detailed essay by Salvadori outlining the philosophy, history, and chief purpose of the Schools for Freedom, a 10-day forum for young liberals held each summer in a different country. Correspondence includes letters from the secretary general of the sponsoring World International to Smith College President Thomas C. Mendenhall and School for Freedom Director Max Salvadori. The letters discuss the selection of a Smith College student participant for the 1967 Ontario, Canada session. Also included is a program from the 1969 Congress held in Munich and "A Liberal's Answer to Communism" by Max Salvadori, published as a supplement by The Liberal International in London.
  - "A Liberal's Answerto Communism," in Supplement, Liberal International 1965 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence 1967 (Box 7)
  - Program, World International Conference 1969 (Box 7)